Guide to the Medicine, Health Care, and Nursing in Montana Oral History Project 1989-1992
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Medicine, Health Care, and Nursing in Montana Oral History Project
1989-1992
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 mhslibrary@mt.gov
{Project Title}
Montana Historical Society
Sound Recording
56 interviews
Number of pages in transcript or summary provided in container list.
This oral history examines the origins of health care and medicine in Montana.
Project History
The early days of medicine in Montana are discussed by physicians, nurses, nurse educators, emergency medical technicians, and lay health care providers.
The project consist of 56 interviews exploring the experiences of longtime physicians, nurses, nurse educators, emergency medical technicians, and lay health care providers in serving the medical needs of Montanans in the twentieth century. Interviewees discuss the impact of weather, distance, and road conditions on treatment; the role new technologies, drugs, and regulations played in expanding services; recruitment of health care professionals to the state; nursing education opportunities in Montana and the region; and home care remedies and treaments prior to modern medicine.
Researchers requesting copies of interviews should refer to the OH number when ordering.
Inventory is arranged by item, with each oral history interview listed by its unique OH number. An abstract for each interview is provided in the inventory to allow keyword searchability. The abstract includes the number of cassettes, CDs or transcript pages for the interview, as appropriate. Researchers requesting copies of interviews should refer to the OH number when ordering.
Collection is open for research.
Interviews in the collection conducted by Montana Historical Society Staff or volunteers.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Research Center catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Medicine; Medical care
Montana
Nurses; Physicians; Emergency medical technicians
Montana; Oral Histories; Sound Recordings; Medicine and Health
- HERBERT TOWNSEND INTERVIEW, OH 1217; 2 tape(s), Summary 19 pages
  Herbert Townsend (b. 1906) discusses his early life in Stevensville, Dillon, and Missoula, Montana; health care during his childhood; the 1930s Depression; employment with Dr. C.R. Thornton (founder of Thornton Hospital); service in the U.S. Army during 1930s; courses in veterinary medicine; service in the U.S. Navy in the Pacific Theater during World War II; work as a carpenter; his ranch; work in a sawmill; electrification of Seeley Lake area in the 1950s; employment with Broken Arrow Ranch; the community of Seeley Lake from 1930s thru 1980s; the local timber industry; and his environmental concerns. Interviewed by John Terreo, September 20, 1990, Seeley Lake, MT.
- BEATRICE KAASCH INTERVIEW, OH 1300; 3 tape(s), Transcript 89 pages
  Beatrice Kaasch (b. 1912), a Fergus County, Montana native, discusses her ancestry and early childhood; homesteading; the 1930s Depression; nursing school; nursing techniques; her job as a science instructor at St. James, St. Vincent, and St. John's hospitals and at Carroll College in Helena; her various nursing positions; changes in nursing education; her work as president of the Montana State Board of Nursing; rural health care; nursing credentials. Interviewed by John Terreo, November 16, 1989, Laurel, MT.
- FRANK NEWMAN INTERVIEW, OH 1301; 2 tape(s), Transcript 41 pages
  Frank Newman discusses rural and community health care; the WAMI (Washington, Montana, and Idaho) Physicians Education and Training Program and his involvement in it; recruitment of health care professionals to Montana's rural areas; WICHE (Western Interstate Commission for Higher Education) rural health delivery systems; HEALTHCON (the electronic information resource system for health professionals); experiences as an instructor of microbiology at Montana State University; academic issues regarding medical education; employment as director of AHEC (the Montana Area Health Education Center); and the Medical Assistance Facilities Demonstration Project. Interviewed by John Terreo, November 21, 1989, Missoula, MT.
- JAN LEISHMAN INTERVIEW, OH 1302; 2 tape(s), Transcript 54 pages
  Jan Leishman discusses her training and education as a student nurse at Montana State University from 1976 to 1981; working in St. Ignatius and at St. James Hospital in Butte; working as a registered nurse/midwife in Bozeman; the affects of liability insurance on midwifery; discrimination; rural health care; credentials. Interviewed by John Terreo, Nov. 21, 1989, Bozeman, Mont.
- ANNA SHANON INTERVIEW, OH 1303; 2 tape(s), Transcript 46 pages
  Anna Shanon (b. 1929) discusses her childhood in Dillon, Montana; experiences as a student nurse at Missouri Baptist Hospital, St. Louis; initial experiences in nursing; work as dean of the Montana State University School of Nursing; organizing the consortium of the Schools of Nursing in Montana; complexities and economics of nursing and nursing education; affects legislative and political issues on nursing. Interviewed by John Terreo, November 22, 1989, Bozeman, MT.
- BERTHA KENISON INTERVIEW, OH 1304; 2 tape(s), Transcript 46 pages
  Bertha Kenison (b. 1913) describes her childhood in Lima, Montana in the 1920s; her work as a nurse's aide at the Barrett Hospital in Dillon from 1959 to 1975; changes in health care; and raising children in Dillon. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 6, 1989, Dillon, MT.
- CLARABEL BOGUT INTERVIEW, OH 1305; 2 tape(s), Transcript 40 pages
  Montana nurse, Clarabel Bogut (b. 1911), discusses her childhood near Malta, Montana; disease and quarantines; training in Deaconess Hospital, Great Falls; her 15-year career as a college nurse at Western Montana College, Dillon; work as a Beaverhead County health nurse. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 6, 1989, Dillon, MT.
- JOHN C. SEIDENSTICKER INTERVIEW, OH 1306; 3 tape(s), Transcript 53 pages
  John Seidensticker (b. 1915) discusses his childhood on a ranch; attending Twin Bridges schools; medical school; service in the army in Europe during World War II; his work as a physician in Madison County, serving the state orphanage and hospitals at Sheridan and Dillon; medical care changes; and his retirement. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 7, 1989, Dillon, MT.
- ALBERT JUERGENS INTERVIEW, OH 1307; 2 tape(s), Summary 12 pages
  Albert Juergens (b. 1918), a physician in Dillon, Montana discusses his medical experiences with the U.S. Army 3rd Infantry in Europe during World War II; his residence in Salmon, Idaho after the war; and establishment of a medical practice in Dillon in 1950; Dillon area medical care, federal government regulations and programs; liability insurance. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 7, 1989, Dillon, MT.
- ANNA PEARL SHERRICK INTERVIEW, OH 1308; 1 tape(s), Transcript 8 pages
  Anna Sherrick discusses her childhood and schooling in Illinois; her instructor's position at Deaconess Hospital in Great Falls; the Montana State University School of Nursing in Bozeman; the U.S. Cadet Nurse Corps during World War II; changes in training; modern medical care. Interviewed by John Terreo, December 6, 1989, Bozeman, MT.
- WILMA CATRON INTERVIEW, OH 1309; 2 tape(s), Transcript 52 pages
  Wilma Catron (b. 1944) discusses her childhood and health care training in Glasgow, Montana; experiences as a nurse's aide at Trinity Hospital, Wolf Point, and Francis Mahon Deaconess Hospital, Glasgow; work as a hospice aide for St. Peter's Hospital, Helena. Interviewed by John Terreo, January 22, 1990, Helena, MT.
- BONNIE ADEE INTERVIEW, OH 1310; 2 tape(s), Transcript 39 pages
  Bonnie Adee (b. 1947) describes her involvement in the St. Peter's Hospital Hospice Program including its early beginnings; its administration by the Westmont Health Services, and its acquisition by St. Peter's in early 1980s; funding of programs; development of volunteer and professional Hospice care nurses, aides, and counselors; affects of liability laws and state and federal legislation on hospices locally and nationally; care of terminally ill people; and philosophies of death. Interviewed by John Terreo, January 23, 1990, Helena, MT.
- GRADY WALTON INTERVIEW, OH 1311; 2 tape(s), Summary 4 pages
  Grady Walton discusses his tenure as administrator of Deaconess Home in Helena, Montana from 1959 to 1962 including staff, children, and facility; the mission of the Home; physical and emotional needs of the children; finances and fund raising; relocation of facility; and initiation of the cottage system. Interviewed by John Terreo, November 30, 1989, Helena, MT.
- KEITH MCCARTY INTERVIEW, OH 1312; 1 tape(s), Summary 8 pages
  Keith McCarty discusses his academic background and his work as project director for the Medical Assistance Demonstration Project in Montana; system for providing limited in-patient service in rural areas as an alternative to hospitals. Interviewed by John Terreo, January 29, 1990, Helena, MT.
- MARGE VANDERHOOF INTERVIEW, OH 1313; 2 tape(s), Transcript 42 pages
  Marge Vanderhoof (b. 1946) describes her education and training as a nursing student in Great Falls and at Montana State University circa 1980 to 1986; her employment as an registered nurse at St. Peter's Hospital in Helena; activities as treasurer of the Montana Nurses Association; and assistance to nurses recovering from drug and alcohol addictions. Interviewed by John Terreo, January 29, 1990, Helena, MT.
- HARRY S. ETTER INTERVIEW, OH 1314; 2 tape(s), Transcript 43 pages
  Harry Etter (b. 1951) discusses his youth as the son of a U.S. Navy physician in Bethesda, Maryland and other areas of the United States; his medical education at the University of Maryland; his internship in San Diego, California; his service as a physician in the U.S. Navy; his service in the submarine squadrons; coming to Montana; his medical practice in Helena, Montana; affects of a busy practice on his family life; general medical practice; medical ethics; affects of technology on health care and the practice of medicine; liability insurance; personal views on life and aging; Medicare and Medicaid; federal and state legislation affecting physicians; and recruitment of physicians to rural areas. Interviewed by John Terreo, February 6, 1990, Helena, MT.
- WILMA NICHOLSON INTERVIEW, OH 1315; 2 tape(s), Transcript 31 pages
  Wilma Nicholson tells about her early life in Seattle, Washington; training, education, and service as a nurse at Providence Hospital in Seattle; her work as a nurse in the coronary care unit at St. James Hospital, Butte, Montana in the early 1960s; experiences as a teacher of students in a vocational program for licensed practical nurses in Butte; other nursing experiences: and work as a Nurse Practitioner at the SOS clinic in Seeley Lake, Montana. Interviewed by John Terreo, February 8, 1990, Seeley Lake, MT.
- VIRGINIA KENYON INTERVIEW, OH 1316; 2 tape(s), Transcript 24 pages
  Virginia Kenyon (b. 1915) discusses her training and education in nursing at Deaconess Hospital, Great Falls beginning in 1932; recollections of Anna Pearl Sherrick; her work as public health nurse in Dawson and Fergus counties Montana from the mid-1930s to 1942; experiences as a U.S. Army nurse with the 81st General Hospital during World War II; her later nursing experiences; and rural nursing. Interviewed by John Terreo, March 23, 1990, Helena, MT.
- MONA VANEK INTERVIEW, OH 1317; 3 tape(s), Transcript 86 pages
  Mona Vanek, a resident of Noxon, Montana discusses health care and living conditions throughout her life; societal attitudes regarding health care; various home remedies such as poultices and mustard plasters; affects of distance on medical care; area hospitals, clinics, and physicians; lice epidemics; childbirth and midwives; prescription and over-the-counter drugs; raising a family; various family illnesses, injuries, and health problems; dentists; the first practicing Physician's Assistant in Western Sanders County; role of Louie and Madge Post in developing local volunteer community ambulance service; increasing costs of medical insurance and health care; medical liability issues; her activities and involvement with the local ambulance service; and Montana's Good Samaritan Law. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 2, 1990, Noxon, MT.
- MARIA SOLCE MYERS INTERVIEW, OH 1318; 2 tape(s), Transcript 56 pages
  Maria Solce Myers (b. 1952), a resident of Heron discusses her work from 1980 to 1990 as an Emergency Medical Technician for the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service; the area in which the Service operates; Montana's Good Samaritan Law; liability insurance; and other issues related to emergency health care. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 2, 1990, Heron, MT.
- JOYCE COUPAL INTERVIEW, OH 1319; 2 tape(s), Transcript 36 pages
  Joyce Coupal (b. 1929) discusses growing up as the daughter of missionaries in India; work as a registered nurse in the maternity ward and clinic of Murray Hospital in Butte; emergency medical treatment of Butte miners; experiences as a Noxon volunteer of the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service; views on quality of medical care in Sanders County. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 3, 1990, Noxon, MT.
- ALICE DETTWILER INTERVIEW, OH 1320; 2 tape(s), Summary 19 pages
  Alice Dettwiler (b. 1927) discusses her early life and health care in Kalispell, Montana; her education, training and nursing work in Minnesota; her return to Montana in 1954; work as an office nurse in the Noxon, Montana clinic from 1962 to 1980; emergency medical transportation in Western Sanders County; work as a school nurse for Noxon High School; and nursing in rural areas. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 5, 1990, Noxon, MT.
- DARRELL AND SONYA HALL INTERVIEWS, OH 1321; 2 tape(s), Transcript 52 pages
  Noxon, Montana residents Darrell Hall and Sonya Hall discuss their involvement with the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service including the organization of the Service; their emergency medical technician training; some of their experiences as members of the ambulance crew; and various aspects of healthcare in western Sanders County. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 5, 1990, Noxon, MT.
- ANITA JOPLING INTERVIEW, OH 1322; 2 tape(s), Summary 18 pages
  Anita Jopling (b. 1913) discusses her experiences as a nursing student at St. Mary's Hospital in Walla Walla, Washington during the early 1930s; work as a nurse at the Veterans Hospital in Walla Walla with veterans of World War I; relocation to Trout Creek, Montana in 1948; her work as Public Health Nurse for Sanders County from 1963 to 1973 the general health care situation in Sanders County; and nursing and health care in very rural areas. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 5, 1990, Trout Creek, MT.
- ELINOR "NAN" COMPTON INTERVIEW, OH 1323; 2 tape(s), Transcript 72 pages
  Elinor Compton (b. 1927) discusses home health care during her childhood in Heron, Montana, and Sandpoint, Idaho; nurses' training and education in the U.S. Cadet Nurses Corps during World War II; initial nursing experiences; work as a nurse during the construction of Noxon Dam; experiences as an office nurse; employment at Bonner Hospital in Sandpoint, Idaho; and rural health care and nursing in Sanders County, Montana. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 5, 1990, Heron, MT.
- THOMAS L. LAWRENCE INTERVIEW, OH 1324; 2 tape(s), Transcript 51 pages
  Thomas Lawrence (b. 1946) discusses health care during his childhood in Kalispell, Montana; medical training and education at the University of South Dakota and University of Colorado; 1972 summer internship in Lewistown, Montana; his general medical practice in Sandpoint, Idaho; life as a physician in a rural area; difficulties in recruiting physicians and other health care professionals to rural communities; his role as supervisor of the ambulance service in Western Sanders County, Montana; legal issues concerning state jurisdictions on emergency medical transportation; and views on medical liability insurance. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 5, 1990, Heron, MT.
- ERABERT STOBIE AND ELDORA STOBIE INTERVIEW, OH 1325; 2 tape(s), Transcript 44 pages
  Erabert (b. 1937) and Eldora Stobie (b. 1937) discuss their role in the organization of the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service; training; daily routines; liability insurance; and accidents. Interviewed by John Terreo, April 6, 1990, Noxon, MT.
- JOHN C. HARKER INTERVIEW, OH 1326; 2 tape(s), Summary 15 pages
  Heron, Montana resident, John Harker (1918-1999), discusses health care in western Sanders County including the services provided by Dr. Osland and Dr. Jones during the 1920s and 1930s; his military service during World War II; logging; and his Christmas tree business. [See also OH 659] Interviewed by John Terreo, April 7, 1990, Heron, MT.
- SHIRLEY MCLINDEN INTERVIEW, OH 1327; 2 tape(s), Transcript 35 pages
  Shirley McLinden, a resident of Trout Creek, Montana, describes her experiences as a member of the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service; her Emergency Medical Technician (EMT) training: ambulance vehicles; the affects of weather and distance; the increase of senior citizens into the county; the history of ambulance service; and liability issues. Interviewed by John Terreo, May 31, 1990, Trout Creek, MT.
- PAUL SEIFERT INTERVIEW, OH 1328; 2 tape(s), Summary 18 pages
  Paul Seifert (1918-2001) discusses his early life in Missoula and Deer Lodge; medical education; hospital residency in Spokane, Washington; U.S. Army service caring for German Prisoners of War (POWs); medical practice in Libby from 1947 to 1987; the affects of government regulations and programs; rural health care; physician recruitment to rural areas; the use of aircraft in medical emergencies; liability insurance; the Libby Hospital. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 3, 1990, Bull Creek, MT.
- DEANA ELDER INTERVIEW, OH 1329; 2 tape(s), Transcript 51 pages
  Deana Elder (b. 1953) discusses trout farm operations in Noxon, Montana; involvement with the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service; her training to become an Emergency Medical Technician (EMT); experiences as a training instructor for the ambulance service; and various medical and legal issues associated in operating a volunteer rural ambulance service; and comparisons between the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service and Libby Ambulance Service. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 4, 1990, Libby, MT.
- LARRY ELDER INTERVIEW, OH 1330; 2 tape(s), Transcript 72 pages
  Larry Elder (b. 1953) discusses trout farm operations in Noxon, Montana; reasons for becoming involved with the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service; training to become an Emergency Medical Technician (EMT); various issues regarding rural emergency medical transportation; affects of weather; and healthcare in very rural areas. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 4, 1990, Libby, MT.
- JESSE BROWN INTERVIEW, OH 1331; 2 tape(s), Transcript 76 pages
  Jesse Brown (b. 1951) discusses his experiences in the navy during the Vietnam conflict as a corpsman with S.E.A.L. (Sea, Air, Land); his teaching and education in the Johns Hopkins physician associates program; his experiences in establishing one of Montana's first satellite clinics at Noxon, Montana; emergency medical transportation in Western Sanders County Montana; involvement with the Western Sanders County Ambulance Service; difficulties in recruiting other health care professionals to rural areas of Montana and elsewhere; and issues concerning medical liability. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 6, 1990, Libby, MT.
- JUDITH C. MACHLER INTERVIEW, OH 1332; 2 tape(s), Transcript 34 pages
  Judith C. Machler (1917-1993) discusses growing up on a homestead north of Lewistown, Montana; home medical remedies; nurses' education and training at St. Joseph's Hospital in Lewistown; the Great Depression; working as a nurse at Deaconess Hospital in Great Falls and the Valley Vista Nursing Home in Lewistown; liability insurance for nurses; changes in nursing over the years; and related issues. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 16, 1990, Billings, MT.
- ROBERTA TAYLOR PULLEN INTERVIEW, OH 1333; 3 tape(s), Transcript 61 pages
  Lewistown, Montana resident Roberta Pullen (b. 1921) describes the osteopathic practice of her father, Dr. Fred Taylor; her mother's child-rearing techniques; quarantine of contagious diseases; the pest house; nurses training at John Hopkins University; her work at Murray Clinic in Butte from 1914 until 1970s. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 19, 1990, Lewistown, MT.
- DONALD R. BROWNE INTERVIEW, OH 1334; 1 tape(s), Summary 11 pages
  Donald Browne (b. 1921), a Lewistown, Montana resident was a member of the advisory boards of St. Joseph's Hospital and the Central Montana Medical Center. He discusses the reasons behind the closing of St. Joseph's and the formation of the Central Montana Medical Facilities; nursing education programs; the construction of the original building and retrofitting it for modern use; the Daughters of Jesus; medical care; and finances. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 20, 1990, Lewistown, MT.
- KEN AND FRANCES "SCOTTIE" BYERLY INTERVIEW, OH 1335; 2 tape(s), Transcript 35 pages
  Frances "Scottie" Byerly (b. 1921) discusses life as the daughter of an army physician in the Philippines, Panama, Hawaii; experiences at the University of North Carolina; marrying Ken Byerly and moving to Lewistown; the Lewistown hospital board; state and federal regulations and the old hospital; county acquiring old hospital, and building a new one; recruiting health care professionals; move to a new hospital during a winter blizzard; and emergency medical transportation. Ken Byerly discusses the history of Lewistown including establishment of St. Joseph's Hospital by Catholic nuns; 1918 flu epidemic; the Depression; working as owner/editor of local newspaper; and fund raising for construction of Central Montana Hospital and other public projects. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 20, 1990, Lewistown, MT.
- ELEANOR HELMER INTERVIEW, OH 1336; 2 tape(s), Transcript 51 pages
  Eleanor Helmer (b. 1929) discusses health care during her childhood in Fergus County, Montana; her nurses' training with the Cadet Nurse Corps in Seattle, Washington; work as a nurse in San Diego, California during the late 1940s; relocation to Lewistown, Montana in 1952; experiences as an obstetrics and surgical nurse, and later Director of Nursing at St. Joseph Hospital in Lewistown; changes in nurse education, individual attitudes and salaries since 1948; management of hospital nurses and other personnel; liability insurance; and other matters. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 22, 1990, Lewistown, MT.
- EARL ECK INTERVIEW, OH 1337; 1 tape(s), Summary 14 pages
  Earl Eck (b. 1908) discusses his pharmaceutical training at Montana State University, Missoula; his early jobs as a pharmacist; pharmaceutical practices; drugs and narcotics; preparation and uses; his relationship with local physicians. Interviewed by John Terreo, June 23, 1990, Lewistown, MT.
- CORRINE DERIANA INTERVIEW, OH 1338; 2 tape(s), Transcript 48 pages